Princess Marie Bonaparte Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Princess Marie Bonaparte Papers 1889-1962 1913-1961
MSS13169
Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962
6,300 items
33 containers
13 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst and author. Journals, correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, legal records, obituaries, genealogical notes, photographs, watercolor drawings, and printed matter relating to Bonaparte's involvement in the field of psychoanalysis.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allendy, René, 1889-1942--Correspondence.; Bibring, Edward, 1894-1959--Correspondence.; Bibring, Grete L. (Grete Lehner), 1899-1977--Correspondence.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962. Cinq cahiers écrits par une petite fille entre sept ans et demi et dix ans et leurs commentaires. 1939-1951.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962. Mémoire des disparus. 1952-1958.; Briand, Aristide, 1862-1932--Correspondence.; Brunswick, Ruth Mack--Correspondence.; Eitingon, M. (Max), 1880-1943--Correspondence.; Federn, Paul--Correspondence.; Ferenczi, Sándor, 1873-1933--Correspondence.; Fliess, Wilhelm, 1858-1928.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Hartmann, Dora, 1902-1974--Correspondence.; Hartmann, Heinz, 1894-1970--Correspondence.; Hesnard, A. (Angelo), 1886-1969--Correspondence.; Jones, Ernest, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Lacan, Jacques, 1901-1981--Correspondence.; Laforgue, René--Correspondence.; Lagache, Daniel, 1903-1972--Correspondence.; Lampl, Hans--Correspondence.; Lampl-de Groot, Jeanne--Correspondence.; Loewenstein, Rudolph Maurice--Correspondence.; Meng, Heinrich, 1887-1972--Correspondence.; Nacht, Sacha, 1901-1977--Correspondence.; Odier, Charles--Correspondence.; Parcheminey, Georges--Correspondence.; Pichon, Edouard, 1890-1940--Correspondence.; Róheim, Géza, 1891-1953--Correspondence.; Sachs, Hanns, 1881-1947--Correspondence.; Saussure, Raymond de, 1894-1971--Correspondence.; Schur, Max--Correspondence.; Williams, Margaret (Lay child analyst)
Organizations
International Psycho-Analytical Association--Correspondence.; Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag--Correspondence.
Subjects
Dreams--Psychological aspects.; Dreams.; Emigration and immigration.; Jewish refugees.; Jews--Mexico--Baja California (Peninsula); Lay analysis (Psychoanalysis); Psychoanalysis--France.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychoanalysts.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.
Places
Baja California (Mexico: Peninsula); Europe--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Emigration and immigration.
Occupations
Authors.; Psychoanalysts.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Princess Marie Bonaparte, psychoanalyst and author, were bequeathed to the Library of Congress by Bonaparte through Anna Freud in 1964. Additional material was given by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1983 and 1987 and by Jeffrey Masson in 1988. A photograph of Bonaparte was purchased in 1999.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Marie Bonaparte are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Some Sigmund Freud correspondence is accessible onsite only via Stacks at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms016046stacks.mss13169.
Online Content
Sigmund Freud correspondence in the papers of Princess Marie Bonaparte is available on the Library of Congress Web site at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000125 and onsite via Stacks at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms016046stacks.mss13169. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1882, July 2 Born, Saint-Cloud, France
1907 Married Prince George of Greece and Denmark (died 1957)
1924 Read Introduction à la psychanalyse. (Paris: 1922), Simon Jankélévitch's translation of Sigmund Freud's introductory lectures on psychoanalysis Published under the pseudonym A. E. Narjani "Considérations sur les causes anatomiques de la frigidité chez la femme," Bruxelles Médical. (Apr. 27)
1925 1927 Analyzed by Sigmund Freud
1926 Founder, Société Psychanalytique de Paris, Paris, France
1927 Founder, Revue française de psychanalyse
1928 Began treating analysands
1929 Provided financial assistance to the nearly bankrupt Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag
1933 Published Edgar Poe. Paris: Denoël et Steele
1934 Founder, Institute de Psychanalyse, Paris, France
1937 Purchased from Reinhold Stahl Sigmund Freud's letters to Wilhelm Fliess Published Topsy, Chow-Chow au poil d'or. Paris: Denoël et Steele
1938 Facilitated the immigration of Sigmund Freud and his family to London, England
1939 1951 Published Cinq cahiers écrits par une petite fille entre sept ans et demi et dix ans et leurs commentaires. Paris: Printed for the author. 4 vols.
1940 Translated and published Métapsychologie, by Sigmund Freud. Paris: Gallimard
1941 1944 Spent war years in Cape Town, South Africa
1946 Published Mythes de guerre. London: Imago Publishing Co.
1950 Secured legal representation for Margaret Williams, a child analyst sued by the Odre des Médecins for practicing medicine without a medical degree
1951 Published De la sexualité de la femme. Paris: Presses universitaires de France
1952 Elected vice president, International Psycho-Analytical Association
1953 Published A la mémoire des disparus. Paris: Printed for the author
1962, Sept.21 Died, Saint-Tropez, France
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Princess Marie Bonaparte (1882-1962) span the years 1889-1962, with the bulk of the material dating from 1913 to 1961. The collection documents Bonaparte's interest and involvement in the field of psychoanalysis. The papers are in French, German, and English and include journals, memoirs, correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, legal documents, obituaries, genealogical notes, photographs, watercolor drawings, and printed matter arranged in five series: General Correspondence, Subject File, Writings, an Addition, and Formerly Closed material.
The General Correspondence series consists of letters to Bonaparte by fellow psychoanalysts including Edward Bibring, Grete L. Bibring, Ruth Mack Brunswick, Max Eitingon, Paul Federn, Sándor Ferenczi, Anna Freud, Dora Hartmann, Heinz Hartmann, Ernest Jones, Hans Lampl, Jeanne Lampl-de Groot, Rudolph Maurice Loewenstein, Heinrich Meng, Géza Róheim, Hanns Sachs, and Max Schur. Relatively few of Bonaparte's outgoing letters are included in the series other than numerous letters written by her to Eitingon between 1925 and 1941.
The General Correspondence series traces Bonaparte's introduction to psychoanalysis in the 1920s and her subsequent rise to prominence in the field due perhaps to her close relationship with Sigmund Freud. The series documents her willingness to expend her personal influence and financial resources on behalf of individual psychoanalysts, psychoanalytic organizations, and publishing endeavors in France and elsewhere. Letters from René Allendy, A. Hesnard, Jacques Lacan, René Laforgue, Daniel Lagache, Sacha Nacht, Charles Odier, George Parcheminey, Edouard Pichon, Raymond de Saussure, and other French psychoanalysts illuminate her role in the establishment and development of psychoanalysis in France. Bonaparte's role in facilitating the emigration of psychoanalysts, most notably Sigmund Freud, from Nazi-controlled countries prior to World War II and the immigration of European analysts to the United States after the war is also documented. The geographical range of Bonaparte's correspondence reflects the extent of the psychoanalytic movement's diaspora and the breadth of her activities and associations.
The Subject File series contains correspondence from the International Psycho-Analytical Association and the Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag, information concerning Bonaparte's purchase of Freud's letters to Wilhelm Fliess in 1937, obituaries and genealogical notes, and a photograph of Bonaparte. Other files relate to Margaret Williams, an American child analyst in Paris who was sued by the French medical establishment for practicing medicine without a medical degree. Included are letters from psychoanalysts pertaining to lay analysis in various countries, copies of interrogatories and depositions, newspaper clippings, and notes by Bonaparte providing an historical survey of lay analysis. Also included in the series is a proposal sent by Bonaparte to William C. Bullitt and Franklin D. Roosevelt in late 1938 recommending that the United States purchase Baja California from Mexico and establish a Jewish refugee state there. Bonaparte noted that she had developed the plan in consultation with Freud.
A small addition contains Bonaparte's notes on Sigmund Freud's letters to Wilhelm Fliess that came open for research use in 2010.
The bulk of the Bonaparte Papers was closed to research use until January 2020. The Formerly Closed series includes Bonaparte's journals dated 1913-1927 and 1959-1961; her dream journals dated 1923-1961; unpublished portions of her memoir; and a series of five original notebooks and watercolor drawings created by Bonaparte as a child that became the basis of her book, Cinq cahiers écrits par une petite fille entre sept ans et demi et dix ans et leurs commentaires. Also in the series are short writings by Bonaparte, many of which are autobiographical. The correspondence includes typescripts of letters exchanged between Bonaparte and the French statesman Aristide Briand between 1914 and 1931. The collection also contains a large number of letters exchanged by Freud and Bonaparte between 1925 and 1939. Also included are a series of notebooks in which Bonaparte recorded the progress of her analysis with Freud.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1914-1961
Subject File, 1923-1962
Writings, 1939
Addition, post-1937
Formerly Closed, 1889-1961
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1914-1961 (Box 1-9)
  Correspondence with related attachments.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Alexander, Franz, 1928, 1934-1940, 1949-1959, undated (Box 1)
  - Allendy, René, 1928-1939
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1938-1960
  - Bernfeld, Siegfried, and Suzanne Bernfeld Cassirer, 1937, 1952-1954
  - Bibring, Edward and Grete L., 1936-1940, 1948-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Breuer, Elsa, 1936-1948
  - Briand, Aristide See Container 15, same heading
  - Brunswick, Ruth Mack, 1925-1945, (8 folders)
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1930-1960, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Cassirer, Suzanne Bernfeld See Container 1, Bernfeld, Siegfried, and Suzanne Bernfeld Cassirer
  - Choisy, Maryse, to Anna Freud, 1946-1947
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1928-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Deutsche, Helene, 1929-1935, 1951
  - "D" miscellaneous, 1946-1960, undated
  - Eissler, K. R. and Ruth, 1938, 1950-1961, (3 folders)
  - Eitingon, Max
    - From, 1927-1946, undated, (5 folders)
    - To, 1925-1941, undated, (3 folders)
  - Empeirikos, Andreas, 1940, 1948-1958 (Box 3)
  - Erikson, Erik, 1933, 1949, undated
  - Federn, Paul, 1933-1938, 1946-1947, undated
  - Ferenczi, Sándor, 1927-1933
  - Flournoy, Henri, 1927-1946, 1952-1955
  - Freud, Anna See Container 15, same heading
  - Freud, Sigmund See Containers 15-19, same heading
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1929-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Garma, Angel, 1936, 1946, 1952-1953, undated
  - Geleerd, Elisabeth R., 1939, 1955-1957
  - Gillespie, William H., 1953-1960, (2 folders)
  - Glover, Edward, 1934-1939, 1949-1953, 1960, undated
  - Greenacre, Phyllis, 1951-1955
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1933-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Hartmann, Heinz and Dora, 1930-1960, undated, (3 folders)
  - Hesnard, A., 1928-1937, 1945-1949, 1960, undated
  - Hoffer, Wilhelm and Hedwig, 1936-1939, 1947-1960, undated
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1932-1959, (2 folders)
  - Jekels, Ludwig, 1929-1939, 1953, undated (Box 4)
  - Jones, Ernest, 1928-1959, undated, (3 folders)
  - Jury, Paul, 1932-1936, 1951-1952
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1932-1951
  - Kouretas, D., 1949-1959, undated
  - Kris, Ernst and Marianne, 1932, 1942-1960
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1938-1960, undated
  - Lacan, Jacques, 1933, 1939, 1948-1952, undated
  - Laforgue, René, 1924-1961, undated, (4 folders)
  - Lagache, Daniel, 1935-1939, 1945-1960, undated
  - Lampl, Hans, and Jeanne Lampl-de Groot, 1936-1940, 1946-1960, (2 folders)
  - Lebovici, Serge, 1952-1959, undated (Box 5)
  - Lechat, Fernand, 1935-1959, undated
  - Lehrman, Philip R., 1929-1932, 1951-1953
  - Leuba, John, 1933-1951, undated
  - Loewenstein, Rudolph Maurice, 1931-1960, undated, (5 folders)
  - Logre, Benjamin Joseph, 1952-1959, undated
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1929-1959, undated, (2 folders)
  - Marty, Pierre, 1940, 1953-1961
  - Meng, Heinrich, 1932-1939, 1955-1960
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1929-1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Nacht, Sacha, 1933-1937, 1947-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1936-1958, undated
  - Odier, Charles and Ilse, 1916-1954, undated, (3 folders)
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1929-1954
  - Pankejeff, Sergius, 1929, 1935-1938, 1946-1947, 1951-1954
  - Parcheminey, Georges, 1928-1953, (2 folders)
  - Pichon, Edouard, 1924-1940, undated, (2 folders)
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1933-1959
  - Ramzy, Ishak, 1953, undated
  - Rodker, John
    - 1939-1948, (2 folders)
    - 1949-1958, undated, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Róheim, Géza
    - 1920, 1928-1939, (6 folders)
    - 1945-1953, undated (Box 8)
  - Roos, Allan, 1960
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1928-1960
  - Sachs, Hanns, 1928-1946, (3 folders)
  - Sachs, Wulf, 1941-1949, undated
  - Sarasin, Philipp, 1933, 1939, 1947-1959
  - Saussure, Raymond de, 1928-1958, undated, (4 folders)
  - Schiff, Paul, 1932-1943
  - Schlumberger, Marc, 1934-1938, 1945, 1950
  - Schur, Max, 1924-1942, 1951-1960, undated, (3 folders)
  - Servadio, Emilio, 1934-1939, 1947-1957
  - Sessions, Barbara, 1931-1939, undated, (2 folders)
  - Simmel, Ernst, 1929-1931
  - Spitz, René A., 1933-1939, 1945-1960, undated
  - Sterba, Richard and Editha, 1934-1937, 1954, undated (Box 9)
  - Storfer, A. J., 1928-1932, 1938, 1943
  - "S" miscellaneous, 1930-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Tamm, Alfhild, 1932-1934
  - Tarachow, Sidney, 1960
  - "V" miscellaneous, 1947-1959
  - Williams, Margaret, 1950-1957, undated See also Container 10, same heading
  - "W" miscellaneous, 1928-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Zavitzianos, George, 1948-1960, undated, (4 folders)
  - Zilboorg, Gregory, 1932
  - Collectively signed letter, postcards, and telegrams, 1935-1960
  - Unidentified, 1937-1940, 1956-1959, undated
- Subject File, 1923-1962 (Box 9-10)
  Correspondence, notes, notebooks, court records, lists, obituaries, genealogical notes, photograph, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Conférence des Psychanalystes de Langue Française, draft of opening remarks, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Freud, Sigmund, letters to Wilhelm Fliess, purchase, 1937 See also Container 21, Letters to Wilhelm Fliess
  - International Psycho-Analytical Association, 1955-1961
  - Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag, 1934, undated
  - Jewish settlement in Baja California, proposal, 1938 (Box 10)
  - Living Thoughts Library, 1938-1939
  - Newspaper clippings, list of, undated
  - Obituaries and genealogical notes, 1961-1962, undated
  - Photograph of Bonaparte, undated
  - William, Margaret, case See also Container 9, same heading
    - Clippings, 1953
    - Correspondence, 1950-1953
    - Court documents, 1951-1953, (3 folders)
    - Notes by Bonaparte, 1951, undated
- Writings, 1939 (Box 10)
  Notes and outlines. Drafts of books and short literary works are filed in the Formerly Closed series.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Notes and outlines, 1939, undated (Box 10)
- Addition, post-1937 (Box 10)
  Bound notebook containing notes by Bonaparte on Sigmund Freud's letters to Wilhelm Fliess.
  Arranged chronologically in a single volume.
  - Notes by Bonaparte on Sigmund Freud's letters to Wilhelm Fliess, post 1937 (Box 10)
- Formerly Closed, 1889-1961 (Box 11-33)
  Journals, correspondence, drafts of writings, notes, notebooks, and watercolor drawings.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Journals (Box 11)
    - Journal No. 1, "Journal d'une femme, le bonheur d'être aimée," 1913-1918, (15 folders)
    - Journal No. 2
      - Outline, undated
      - Text
        - 1919
        - 1920
          - Jan. 13-30, (2 folders)
          - Feb. 1-May 4 (Box 12)
        - 1921-1922, (10 folders)
        - 1923 (Box 13)
        - 1924
          - Jan. 24-Sept. 5, (3 folders)
          - Sept. 24-Dec. 29 (Box 14)
        - 1925-1927, (5 folders)
    - "Journal de ma vieillesse," 1959-1961, (5 folders)
  - General Correspondence (Box 15)
    - Briand, Aristide
      - From, 1918-1925, (5 folders)
      - To, 1914-1931, (8 folders)
    - Freud, Anna, 1960-1961
    - Freud, Sigmund
      - From
        - 1925
        - 1926, Mar.-Apr.
        - 1926, May-June
        - 1926, Aug.-Dec.
        - 1927, Jan.-May
        - 1927, June-Dec.
        - 1928, Jan.-Apr.
        - 1928, May-June (Box 16)
        - 1928, July-Nov.
        - 1929, Jan.-Apr.
        - 1929, May-Dec.
        - 1930. Jan.-May
        - 1930, June-Dec.
        - 1931, Jan.-June
        - 1931, July-Dec.
        - 1932, Jan.-May
        - 1932, June-Sept.
        - 1932, Oct.-Dec.
        - 1933, Jan.-June
        - 1933, July-Dec.
        - 1934, Jan.-Apr.
        - 1934, May-Dec.
        - 1935
        - 1936, Jan.-June
        - 1936, July-Dec.
        - 1937, Jan.-Apr.
        - 1937, May-July
        - 1937, Aug.-Dec.
        - 1938, Jan.-Aug. (Box 17)
        - 1938, Sept.-Dec.
        - 1939
      - To
        - 1925
        - 1926, Feb.-Mar.
        - 1926, Apr.
        - 1926, May
        - 1926, June
        - 1926, July-Aug.
        - 1926, Sept.
        - 1926, Nov.-Dec.
        - 1927, Jan.-Apr.
        - 1927, May-June
        - 1927, July
        - 1927, Aug.-Dec.
        - 1928, Jan.-Feb. (Box 18)
        - 1928, Mar.-Apr.
        - 1928, May-June
        - 1928, July-Nov.
        - 1929, Jan.-Mar.
        - 1929, Apr.-June
        - 1929, July-Dec.
        - 1930, Jan.-Mar.
        - 1930, Apr.-Aug.
        - 1930, Sept.-Dec.
        - 1931, Jan.-Sept.
        - 1931, Oct.-Dec.
        - 1932, Jan.-June
        - 1932, July-Sept.
        - 1932, Oct.-Dec.
        - 1933, Jan.-May (Box 19)
        - 1933, June-Dec.
        - 1934
        - 1935, Jan.-July
        - 1935, Aug.-Dec.
        - 1936, Jan.-Sept.
        - 1936, Oct.-Dec.
        - 1937, Jan.-May
        - 1937, June-Dec.
        - 1938, Jan.-Aug.
        - 1938, Sept.-Dec.
        - 1939
      - To Freud and Bonaparte from others enclosed in the Freud-Bonaparte correspondence, 1926-1939
  - Subject File (Box 20)
    - Dreams, notes
      - 1923-1940, (14 folders)
      - 1941-1961, (12 folders) (Box 21)
    - Freud, Sigmund
      - Letters to Wilhelm Fliess, purchase, 1936-1937, 1951-1954
      - List and excerpts of Freud's letters to Bonaparte cited in Ernest Jones's biography of Freud, 1961
      - Medical treatment by Antoine Lacassagne, 1939, 1954
      - Record of Bonaparte's analysis (Box 22)
        - Notebooks
          - 1925, Oct. 1-Nov. 16, (9 folders)
          - 1925, Nov. 17-1926, Jan. 7, (7 folders) (Box 23)
          - 1926, Jan. 8-Feb. 25, (7 folders) (Box 24)
          - 1926, July 12-1931, Sept. 12, (6 folders) (Box 25)
        - Selected excerpts, 1925-1929
          - Handwritten, (3 folders)
          - Typescript, (2 folders)
  - Writings (Box 26)
    - Books
      - A la mémoire des disparus, unpublished portions, (13 folders)
      - A la mémoire des disparus, unpublished portions, (15 folders) (Box 27)
      - A la mémoire des disparus, unpublished portions, (15 folders) (Box 28)
      - A la mémoire des disparus, unpublished portions, (16 folders) (Box 29)
      - A la mémoire des disparus, unpublished portions, (10 folders) (Box 30)
      - Cinq cahiers écrit par une petite fille entre sept ans et dix ans et leur commentaires (Box 31)
        - Notebooks, 1889-1892, (5 folders)
        - Watercolor drawings, 1889
    - Short literary works
      - "Le bonheur d'être aimée," 1914-1919, undated, (4 folders)
      - "La chambre aux rideaux d'or," 1920-1921, (2 folders)
      - "Deutsche Gedichte," 1943-1946, undated
      - "Exil austral," 1941-1943, (2 folders)
      - "Le Fils," 1937
      - "La Guerre et mon fils," 1941
      - "Les Lettres brulées," 1929, (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - "Le Livre de l'enfant et des bêtes," undated
      - "Une Mère et un fils," undated
      - "La Moitié d'un coeur," undated, (6 folders)
      - "Les Murs," undated
      - "Narcisse au soleil couchant," undated
      - "Pascal," 1926-1927, (2 folders)
      - "Le Passage de Sappho," circa 1947-1948 (Box 33)
      - "La Survivante," 1915-1919
      - "Vaga," 1961, undated, (4 folders)
      - "Le Vieux Compagnon," 1939